# 大家好 剛才看到兄弟 匆匆忙忙的跑進山上去啦
Hi everyone! I just saw my buddy, rushing to the hill.
# 我以為他摘果呢 嚇我一大跳
I thought that he was gonna pick the fruits. It scared me.
# 搞得我開車直接衝進來啦
So I also rushed here right away, driving my car.
# 我看一下啊我那個果還在不在
Let me see whether my, my fruits are still there.
# 就在前面
They’re right in the front.
# 還好 還在
Still there, fortunately
# 那麼多 還沒熟
There are so many, but are still green.
# 概[SIC]不到 概不到他不摘
No wonder he didn’t pick them.
# 不知道他進山幹嘛
So why was he going into the hill?
# 我去看一下前面 前面還有那個鐵老虎哦
Let’s have a look in the front. There are also "iron tigers" (big kadsura fruits) in the front,
# 還有酒飯團 還有 那麼甚麼
and "jiu fantuan" (kadsura fruits) too. And also, well, you know,
# 額 酸棗 都還很多 我去摘一點來
eh, hog plums, at a lot more. Let me go and pick some.
# 帶了一個小籃子
I go with a small basket.
# 今天沒下雨 你看 一下就上來啦
There’s no rain today. Look! I can go up right away.
# 小意思上這樣的坡
This slope is a piece of cake.
# 這個車很猛的
This car is not to be sniffed at.
# 你看 這裡好多拿藤果啊
Look! Here are a lot of wild chocolate vine fruits.
# 好多哇
Really a lot!
# 一樹都是
All over the tree
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 哎呀 這裡勾住啦
Aya! I am hooked here.
# 你看 那麼多拿藤果
Look! So many chocolate vine fruits
# 一樹都是 這裡有幾個
All over the three. Some here,
# 那裡有 那裡有 那裡也有
some there, and there, and there as well
# 好多哇 今年
Really a lot, this year
# 我去前面看一下 前面有沒有香藤子
Let me go in the front, and see if there are any “xiang tengzi” (valarien) in the front.
# 去年我都摘了幾個香藤子 今年應該有
I picked some valariens last year. This year should be no exception.
# 你看 這個茶花
Look! These are tea flowers.
# 這個不知道哪裡種的 這裡怎麼有一棵這樣的茶花
I have no ideas who planted it. Why is such a tea flower tree here?
# 這個時候 這個季節都是 那個茶果子都快熟啦
At this moment, in this season, the tea fruits are already becoming ripe.
# 他現在才剛開花
But this is still blossoming,
# 而且還開了那麼多花
and blossoming so gorgeously,
# 開的花枝招展
with so many flowers.
# 誒
Ey?
# 哎呀 好像那邊有野豬哦
Aiya! There seems to be some wild boars.
# 看一下
Let me take a look.
# 誒 我以為是甚麼呢 原來是
Ey! I was wondering what they are. But it turns out to be,
# 那個 小山羊
you know, little goats.
# 沒有要的就是野山羊
They belong to no one. So they’re wild goats.
# 放在那 放在荒效野外
They are left, left in the wild.
# hello
Hello!
# 下午好 哎呀
Good afternoon! Aya!
# 那麼多
There are so many!
# 咩
Meh~
# 咩 你看 那頭領頭羊
Meh~ Look! That one is the Alpha,
# 好黑的 肚子白的那個
the very black one, with a white belly.
# 應該有一百斤 那麼大
It should be at least fifty kilograms. It’s so big.
# 全身肌肉
It’s covered with muscles.
# 肯定好吃
So it must be very tasty,
# 咩 全跑啦
Meh! They all ran away.
# 好多小山羊
A lot of small goats.
# 你看 這野果
Look! These wild fruits…
# 好多吧
There are a lot, right?
# 剛我這一眼看上去都七八個哦1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
My first sight can already see seven or eight, 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9.
# 還沒熟 熟的時候再來
But they’re not yet ripe. Let me come again when they’re ripe.
# 先做好標記來
I put a mark here first.
# 記得從這裡插一個這個東西就知道
I just need to remember that this thing is stuck here.
# 一個樹枝就知道這裡
A branch is enough to remind myself.
# 這次把標記做好啦 直奔主題
When the mark is properly done this time. Next time, right to the main theme!
# 看一下前面還有些甚麼東西
Let me see what else in the front.
# 你看 這個 我們這邊叫
Look! This is, here it is called,
# 火柴品
match heads.
# 就是火柴火柴頭一樣的
Well, they just look like matches, match heads.
# 火柴頭就是這樣子的
This is how match heads look like.
# 很靚吧 這個可以吃的 這個 不過特別酸
Beautiful, aren’t they? These are also edible, these fruits. But, they’re exceptionally sour.
# 嗯 怎麼那麼好吃
Um? Why does it taste so good?
# 嗯
Um!
# 好酸
It’s really sour.
# 啊 你看
Ah! Look!
# 靚吧
Beautiful, aren’t they?
# 如果打 打了霜之後更靚
They would be even more beautiful after, after being frosted.
# 通紅的 而且有點甜甜的 酸酸甜甜的 特別好吃
It would be completely red, with a bit sweet, sweet and sour, exceptionally tasty.
# 現在還不是很熟
They’re still not really that ripe now.
# 掛在樹上給鳥吃
I hang it onto the tree for the birds.
# 到時候鳥就過來吃掉啦 不會浪費
The birds can eat it when they come in a while. Then it would not be wasted.
# 不能浪費資源
We shouldn’t waste any resources on our planet.
# 你看 這裡有 酒飯團
Look! Here are “jiu fantuan” (lit: wined rice ball, small kadsura fruits).
# 那麼小的酒飯團
The “jiu fantuan” are so small.
# 還沒熟
But they’re not yet ripe.
# 熟了在[SIC]說
Let’s wait until they’re ripe.
# 你看
Look!
# 這太壞啦 被松鼠咬下來啦
It’s too bad. It was bitten off by squirrels.
# 這個都還沒熟就被它咬下來啦
It’s still green but they bit it off.
# 哎喲
Aya!
# 裡面有肉哦 (註︰原字幕缺失了，但太清楚，不想跳過)
Here’s pulp inside.
# 太浪費啦
What a waste!
# 這麼壞
They’re so bad!
# 你看 這個我們這裡叫狐狸桃
Look! These are called “fox fruits” (wild kiwifruits) here.
# 還沒熟 要冬天才熟
But they’re not yet ripe, not until winter.
# 好多哇
Really a lot!
# 很好吃的哦
They’re really tasty, you know.
# 拿到一捏一吸就進去啦
Take it, squeeze it, suck it, and it’s in your mouth.
# 皮就一丟
Then throw away the peel.
# 現在沒熟
But they're not yet ripe.
# 你看 一隻老鷹在天空中盤旋
Look! An eagle is circling around in the sky.
# 你是不是想捉我啊
Are you coming to catch me?
# 來呀
C’mon! Go head!
# 把我勾上 勾上天空上去也好啊
Hook me, hook me into the sky. It would be really nice!
# 你看 這裡一塊 很紅的哦 香藤子
Look! The whole area here, is really red, the “xiang tengzi”
# 你看
Look!
# 夠紅吧 這個
They’re really red, right?
# 這個味道很好吃的哦 這種味道
The taste is really good, you know. This taste is,
# 就是那種
is just like,
# 有點辣辣的 辣嘴巴 這個
it's a bit spicy, it burns the mouth, sort of.
# 很甜
It’s really sweet.
# 它有點辣辣的 甜中帶辣 辣中帶甜
A bit spicy, sweety spicy, spicy sweet,
# 還有一種果香味
with a fruity scent.
# 啊 全部把它摘下來
Ah! Let me pick them all.
# 那還有幾個
There are still a few.
# 那麼小
They’re so small.
# 這個靚
This is beautiful!
# 哎喲 差點掉啦
Aya! It almost dropped onto the ground.
# 好靚吧
Beautiful, aren’t they?
# 你看 這個就熟透了的香藤子
Look! These are completely ripe “xiang tengzi”.
# 剛才 剛才那個 在路邊上的沒熟的
The, the one, the ones on the road were not yet ripe.
# 熟透了就這種產色 血紅色
This is the colour when they're completely ripe, bloody red.
# 看一下前面還有沒有
Let’s see if there are any more in the front.
# 你看 這樹上
Look! In this tree,
# 有五六串哦 這樹太高啦
there are five or six strings of them. But this tree is too tall,
# 只能把樹砍掉才可以摘
we can only chop down the tree if we want to pick them.
# 這樣
But it’s,
# 這樣不好 不能亂砍樹
it’s no good. Trees need to be protected.
# 哇 你看
Wa! Look!
# 這有兩個哦 那麼大的
Here are two. They’re so big!
# 它現在沒熟哦
But they’re not yet ripe.
# 你看 這兩個鐵老虎
Look! These two iron tigers (big kadsura fruits),
# 那麼大了哦
they’re so big now.
# 比我拳頭還大
even bigger than my fist,
# 跟碗一樣
just like a bowl.
# 現在還沒熟哦 熟了之後我再來
But they’re not yet ripe. When they’re ripe, I’ll come again,
# 再來摘
come and pick them.
# 來早了
I come too early.
# 來遲了又怕被人家 吃
But if we come late, it might have already been, eaten,
# 摘掉
picked, by other people.
# 在樹頂上的還有兩個好大的
There are also two very big ones at the top of the tree.
# 你看 這裡的拿藤果
Look! The chocolate vine fruits here,
# 那麼大條的
are so big and long.
# 苗又少 肉又多
There are not many leaves. But the pulp is rich.
# 個 個頭又大
And the size, the size is really big.
# 說明這裡的肥料好
It means that here is will fertilised.
# 兄弟在這裡放牛
My buddy pastures his cattle here.
# 天天拉牛屎在這裡
And the cattle poop here every day.
# 怪不很它那麼大
No wonder they’re so big.
# 你看 又好多金櫻子啊
Look! Here are also a lot of rose fruits.
# 好多刺的
They're very spiky.
# 它這個也可以用來泡酒的哦
These can also be used to make infused liquour, you know.
# 也可以把那個
They can also be, you know,
# 直接吃也可以 但是要把裡面的籽挖掉
be eaten right away. But the seeds inside need to be removed.
# 還有外面的刺也把它
And the spikes on the surface also need to be,
# 搓掉
rubbed off.
# 直接吃就好
Then they can be eaten right away.
# 好多啊 今年
There are a lot, this year.
# 今年好像甚麼野果都很多
It seems that all wild fruits are plentiful this year.
# 你看 這個茶果哦
Look! This is a tea fruit.
# 這就是我剛剛說的那個茶樹果
This is the fruit of the tea tree that I just mentioned before.
# 這個苞啊 裡面都是籽來的
This pocket, there are only seeds inside.
# 這個可以用來榨油的哦
Oil can be extracted from it, you know.
# 這裡也可以榨個幾滴油出來喲
A few drops of oil can be extracted here.
# 你看 這裡還有杮子哦 這個杮子快黃啦
Look! Here are also persimmons. These persimmons will soon be turning yellow.
# 你看
Look!
# 這裡一個那麼大串的
Look! Here’s such a huge string of “xiang tengzi”.
# 好久都沒有 沒有爬過 竹竿啦
I haven’t climbed, haven't climbed a, a bamboo for a long time.
# 我上試一下能不能 還能不能爬的上去
Let me try if I still can, if I still can climb onto it.
# 這個可以
It’s not bad.
# 半斤
A quarter kilogram
# 這樣的是熟透了這個
This one is completely ripe, this one.
# 嘗一下
Let me have a try.
# 這種才好吃哦
This would taste the best.
# 嗯
Um!
# 就是不一樣
The difference is significant.
# 你看 這兩個最大的
Look! These two are the biggest ones.
# 太好吃啦
It’s simply delicious!
# 帶回給小孩子吃
Let’s take them back for our children.
# 他們見都沒見過這個果
They haven’t even seen this kind of fruits before.
# 還有
There’s,
# 那還有一棵
there’s another tree.
# 很累的哦
It’s really tiring, you know.
# 哎呀 就摘了快一籃子啦
Aya! This basket is nearly full.
# 我看一下前面還有沒有
Let me see if there are any more in the front.
# 好久沒上山啦
I haven’t been to the hill for a very long time.
# 現在我都胖啦
I’m becoming chubby now.
# 兩腿發軟
And my legs are trembling.
# 你看
Look!
# 這樹上還有那個山茘枝哦
There are even wild lychee in this tree.
# 我都還沒發現
I didn’t see them.
# 我都 我差不多20年 20年都沒吃過這個 這個東西啦
I haven’t, haven’t eaten these, these things for almost twenty years, twenty years.
# 好少啦
They’re really rare.
# 竟然被我碰上啦
But fate brings them to me today.
# 我上去搖一下看搖不搖得不來
Let me go up and shake it. See if I can shake them off.
# 哎呀紅的都被掉下去啦
Aya! The red ones are all shaken off.
# 剩下不紅的就放在這裡
Those which are still here are not red.
# 你看
Look!
# 就摘了那麼一點
So I’ve just picked a tiny little bit here.
# 嘗一下 看一下怎麼樣 味道
Let me try, and see how, how it tastes.
# 一捏一下
Squeeze it.
# 好甜
Really sweet
# 有點像茘枝味一樣
It tastes a bit like lychee.
# 別浪 不要浪費啦 差點掉啦
Don’t, don’t waste it! It almost dropped.
# 好 回去啦 回去啦
Alright! Let’s go back, let’s go back.
# 你看 檢了那麼一點點
Look! We’ve picked just a tiny little bit here.
# 回去啦
Let’s go back.
# 看一下前面還有沒有甚它的
Let me see if there's anything else in the front.
# 你看 這個樹
Have a look at this tree.
# 又大又紅的哦
They’re all big and red, you know.
# 叫兄弟上去搖一下
I ask my buddy to go up and shake it.
# 先把那帽子跟衣服拿過來 褲子也可以
Give me your hat and your shirt first, or your trousers, if you prefer.
# 把衣服也拿過來
Give me your shirt as well.
# 好
Alight!
# 開始了啊
Let’s start.
# 等一下 等一下 攤好來
Wait, wait! Let me spread it here first.
# 可以 開始搖
Alright! Start shaking!
# (一個都沒有)
Not even one!
# 你看 這個 超級大的
Look! This is, super huge.
# 還有這個 小的
And this one, a small one.
# 這個帽子就接了兩個
So two are caught with this hat.
# 先吃個小的來
Let me have the small one first.
# 嗯 嗯
Um, um!
# 特別香
It smells exceptionally good.
# 果肉黃的 這個留給攝影小哥吃
The pulp is brown. I leave this one for Mr. Cameraman.
# 他帽子接的
It’s caught with his hat, after all.
# 你看
Look!
# 這裡這個皮是這樣子的哦
That’s how their peels look like, you know.
# 它這個表皮上像那個 獼猴桃一樣的
The peel looks like the, I mean, just like kiwifruits.
# 但不 不影響它的口感
But it, it tastes as good.
# 你看 好多啊
Look! Here are a lot!
# 那邊 那樹上還好多
There, a lot more on that tree.
# 下次把那夾子帶過來就可以啦
I shall come again with that pincer next time.
# 好夾 這樣
It would then be much easier.
# 樹枝太小 上次 我記得我去年就在這裡上面
The branches are too small. Last time, I remember filling up half,
# 搞了 搞了半蛇皮袋
half a bag up there last year.
# 半牛皮袋
Half a bag
# 哇 你看 這一樹都是哦
Wa! Look! They’re all over the tree.
# 好多哇
A lot!
# 應該可以把籃子裝滿啦
I think I can fill up this basket now.
# 天都快黑啦
It will be dark very soon.
# 黑了我也要
I don’t care. I am going up and pick them,
# 我也上去摘
dark or not.
# 這個爽吧 這個
This is really cool, this one!
# 嘗一下
Let me try.
# 這裡還有這麼多小果子
Here are still so many tiny fruits.
# 是啊
Indeed!
# 一個小籃子都裝滿啦
This small basket is already full.
# 你看 這裡還有那麼多這個
Look! Here are so many, this is,
# 這個叫甚麼
how is it called?
# 我們這邊叫做紅扣子
Here they're called red buttons.
# 這個可以吃的哦 這個
It’s edible, you know.
# 你看
Look!
# 酸酸甜甜的
It’s sweet and sour,
# 像葡萄一樣
just like grapes.
# 不信你嘗一下 你要吃一下
Don’t you think so? You can have a try. You gotta have a try.
# 這樣一串一串
They’re in strings.
# 天色晚啦 我要回去啦
It’s getting dark now and I gotta go back.
# 一籃子 裝都裝不下啦
A whole basket. It can't take any more.
# 回去 回去
Let’s go, let’s go.
# 等下天黑啦 就出不來山啦
We would get stuck in the hill if it gets dark.
# 是甚麼東西 這個
What is it? This one
# 這個像腎一樣的
It looks like a kidney.
# (我們這邊叫XXXXXX)
Here it’s called, it's called ????? (untranslatable and untransliterable).
# 聽說這個玩了 會爛手的
People say that, it burns our hands.
# 但是看上去
But it looks…
# 好香啊
It smells so good.
# 我幫我剝啊 裡面的籽不能吃的 這個是辣的啊
Let me peel it. The seed inside is not to be eaten, alright? It’s spicy, you know.
# 好不好吃
Does it taste good?
# 籽不要啊
Don’t swallow the seed!
# 吃不了就哇出來啊
Spit it out if you can’t take it.
# 全部吐掉啦
She spits everything out.
# 好不好吃
Does it taste good?
# 是有一點辣辣的 是不是
It’s a bit spicy, isn’t it?
# 那你吃葡萄
Then have some grapes,
# 小葡萄
tiny grapes!
# 皮不能吃的哈
Don’t eat the peel, alright?
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦 你看 你看他
Alright! The video ends here. Look! Have a look at him!
# (啊 一個像葡萄一樣的)
Ah! It looks just like a tiny grape.
# (全吃完啦)
They've already finished everything.